<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sect1 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="axonivyportal.customization.taskdetails">
	<title>Task widget</title>	
	<para>TaskWidget is a built-in component of Portal which contains the tasks users can interact with.
	In order to show needed task's information, Portal supports overriding concept for TaskWidget. 
	Each TaskWidget contains 2 parts:
	</para>
	<orderedlist>
		<listitem>
			<para><link linkend="axonivyportal.customization.taskwidget.howtooverideui">UI</link>: TaskHeader and TaskListHeader and TaskBody and TaskFilter</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para><link linkend="axonivyportal.customization.taskwidget.howtooverridedataquery">Data query</link>: display the tasks as you want</para>
		</listitem>
	</orderedlist>
	<important>
		<para>
			<orderedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>Task header customization does not support responsive design, smaller resolutions (iPad, etc.)</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Additional properties cannot be displayed right now as a column</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Task header's buttons cannot be modified (they stay where they are)</para>
				</listitem>
			</orderedlist>
		</para>
	</important>
	<sect2 xml:id="axonivyportal.customization.taskwidget.howtooverideui">
		<title>How to override task widget's UI</title>
        <para>Refer to <code>PortalExamples</code> project for examples</para>
		<para>
			<orderedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Introduce an Axon.ivy project which has <code>PortalTemplate</code> as a required library.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						To customize task widget, you must customize Portal Home first. Refer to <link linkend="axonivyportal.customization.portalhome">Customize Portal home</link> to set new home page.
					</para>
				</listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    Copy the <code>PortalStart</code> process from <code>PortalTemplate</code> to your project. Point PortalHome element to your custom home page in previous step. This process is new home page and administrator should register this link by Portal's Admin Settings.  
                  </para>
                </listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Override Task widget in: TaskList page, Task Search result, Relate tasks of a case, History tasks of a case.
						<itemizedlist>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									Introduce a new HTMLDialog which uses template <code>/layouts/PortalTasksTemplate.xhtml</code> (refer to <link linkend="axonivyportal.components.layouttemplates.reponsiveness">Responsiveness</link> to override responsiveness). You can take a look at <code>PortalTasks.xhtml</code> to see how to customize it.
									<tip>
										<para>Highly recommend to copy the <code>PortalTasks</code> HTMLDialog in PortalTemplate and change the copied one's view.</para>
									</tip>
								</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								Use Axon.ivy Override to override the <code>OpenPortalTasks</code> callable. The original implementation of this callable is calling <code>PortalTasks</code>, change it to call the customized Page introduced in the step above. The signature of this callable is <code>useView(TaskView)</code> and customized page must receive this <code>TaskView</code> instance, put in the dialog's <code>Data</code> with the exact name <code>taskView</code>.
							</listitem>
						</itemizedlist>
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						After previous steps, you can override <link linkend="axonivyportal.customization.taskwidget.howtooverideui.taskheader">TaskHeader and TaskListHeader</link> and <link linkend="axonivyportal.customization.taskwidget.howtooverideui.taskbody">TaskBody</link> and <link linkend="axonivyportal.customization.taskwidget.howtooverideui.taskfilter">TaskFilter</link>
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</orderedlist>
			<sect3 xml:id="axonivyportal.customization.taskwidget.howtooverideui.taskheader">
				<title>Task header</title>
				<para>
					Refer to the <code>taskListHeader</code> and <code>taskHeader</code> sections in <code>PortalTasks.xhtml</code> of PortalTemplate. In case your task widget has new columns, you should override TaskLazyDataModel to make the sort function of these columns work:
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem>
							<para>Introduce a java class extends TaskLazyDataModel</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para>Override the <code>extendSort</code> method, the <code>extendSortTasksInNotDisplayedTaskMap</code> method and extend the sort function for the added columns (see the methods' Javadoc comments)</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para>Default taskList supports user to config display/hide column
								<mediaobject>
									<imageobject>
										<imagedata fileref="images/TaskWidget/TaskColumnsConfiguration.png" />
									</imageobject>
								</mediaobject>
								<para>
									<itemizedlist>
										<listitem>
											<para>In case you has new columns, override method <code>getDefaultColumns</code> of the extended class from TaskLazyDataModel to display checkboxes in Config columns panel and display/hide sortFields (see the methods' Javadoc comments)</para>
										</listitem>
										<listitem>
											<para>To add cms for checkboxes's label, add new entries to folder <code>/ch.ivy.addon.portalkit.ui.jsf/taskList/defaultColumns/</code> in <code>PortalStyle</code> or override method <code>getColumnLabel</code>(see the methods' Javadoc comments)</para>
										</listitem>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>In <code>taskListHeader</code> section, use <code>TaskColumnHeader</code> component</para>
                                        </listitem>
										<listitem>
											<para>In <code>taskHeader</code> section, use <code>TaskCustomField</code> component for each additional columns. This component will handle display/hide new columns on task list.</para>
                                            <para>Currently, TaskCustomField only supports text field. If you want to create your own component, remember to add rendered="#{taskView.dataModel.isSelectedColumn('YOUR_CUSTOM_COLUMN')}" </para>
											<para>
												For example: Show custom field <code>customer name</code> which stored in <code>task.customVarCharField5</code>
												<para>
													<code>&lt;ic:ch.ivy.addon.portalkit.component.task.column.TaskCustomField id="customer-name-component" componentId="customer-name" column="customVarCharField5" dataModel="#{taskView.dataModel}" labelValue="#{task.customVarCharField5}" /&gt;</code>
												</para>
											</para>
										</listitem>
									</itemizedlist>
								</para>
							</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para>Use Axon.ivy Override to override the <code>InitializeTaskDataModel</code> callable and initialize data model by your customized one.</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para>In your customized portal tasks HTMLDialog, the customized data model should be passed as a parameter to components (refer to <code>PortalTasks.xhtml</code>).</para>
						</listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
				</para>
			</sect3>
			<sect3 xml:id="axonivyportal.customization.taskwidget.howtooverideui.taskbody">
				<title>Task body</title>
				<para>
					Refer to the <code>taskBody</code> section in <code>PortalTasks.xhtml</code> of PortalTemplate.
				</para>
				<para>
					If you need to apply the responsiveness behavior of Portal for task details, there are 2 components which can be used: <code>ResponsivenessHandleContainer</code> and <code>ResponsivenessHandleButton</code>:
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem>
							<para>
								ResponsivenessHandleContainer: a container contains <code>ResponsivenessHandleButton</code> and your javascript which contains the onstart and oncomplete function of <code>ResponsivenessHandleButton</code>.
							</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para>
								ResponsivenessHandleButton: contains the params which handle responsiveness:
								<para>
									<itemizedlist>
										<listitem>
											<para>
												icon: the icon of button
											</para>
										</listitem>
										<listitem>
											<para>
												displayedSelectors: css selectors of the components which need to be displayed.
											</para>
										</listitem>
										<listitem>
											<para>
												hiddenSelectorsInLargeScreen: css selectors of the components which need to be hidden in large screen (width: 1920).
											</para>
										</listitem>
										<listitem>
											<para>
												hiddenSelectorsInMediumScreen: css selectors of the components which need to be hidden in medium screen (width: 1366).
											</para>
										</listitem>
										<listitem>
											<para>
												hiddenSelectorsInSmallScreen: css selectors of the components which need to be hidden in small screen (width: 1024).
											</para>
										</listitem>
										<listitem>
											<para>
												fadeTime: the fade in/out time.
											</para>
										</listitem>
										<listitem>
											<para>
												onstart: client side callback to execute before responsiveness execution.
											</para>
										</listitem>
										<listitem>
											<para>
												oncomplete: client side callback to execute after responsiveness execution.
											</para>
										</listitem>
									</itemizedlist>
								</para> 
							</para>
						</listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
					<para>
						For example:
						<para>
								<code>&lt;ui:composition template="/layouts/PortalTasksTemplate.xhtml"&gt;</code>
						</para>
						<para>
								<code>&lt;ui:param name="useOverrideBody" value="true" /&gt;</code>
						</para>
						<para>
								<code>&lt;ui:define name="taskBody"&gt;</code>
						</para>
						<para>
								<code>Customized content</code>
						</para>
						<para>
								<code>&lt;ic:ch.ivy.addon.portalkit.component.ResponsivenessHandleContainer styleClass="hidden-lg"&gt;</code>
						</para>
						<para>
								<code>&lt;ic:ch.ivy.addon.portalkit.component.ResponsivenessHandleButton icon="fa fa-file js-note-column-responsive-button" displayedSelectors="['#task-note']" hiddenSelectorsInMediumScreen="['.task-details .replaced']" hiddenSelectorsInSmallScreen="['.task-details .replaced']" /&gt;</code>
						</para>
						<para>
								<code>&lt;h:outputScript library="js" name="task-detail-default-responsiveness.js" /&gt;</code>
						</para>
						<para>
								<code>&lt;/ic:ch.ivy.addon.portalkit.component.ResponsivenessHandleContainer&gt;</code>
						</para>
						<para>
								<code>&lt;/ui:define&gt;</code>
						</para>
						<para>
								<code>&lt;/ui:composition&gt;</code>
						</para>
					</para>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="images/TaskWidget/TaskDetailsResponsiveness.png" />
						</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</para>
			</sect3>
			<sect3 xml:id="axonivyportal.customization.taskwidget.howtooverideui.taskfilter">
				<title>Task filter</title>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>Refer to the <code>taskFilter</code> section in <code>PortalTasks.xhtml</code> of PortalTemplate.</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>In order to introduce new filter, create a new java class extends TaskFilter and override its methods (see javadoc comments)</para>
						<mediaobject>
							<imageobject>
								<imagedata fileref="images/TaskWidget/TaskFilter.png" />
							</imageobject>
						</mediaobject>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>Introduce a java class extends TaskFilterContainer. This filter container contains your filters, you can reuse default filters, refer to <code>DefaultTaskFilterContainer.java</code></para>
						<tip><para>StateFilter is added as default to container. If you don't need it, use this code in constructor: <code>filters.remove(stateFilter);</code></para></tip>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>Introduce a java class extends TaskLazyDataModel. Override the <code>initFilterContainer</code> method and initialize filter container (see javadoc comments)</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>Use Axon.ivy Override to override the <code>InitializeTaskDataModel</code> callable and initialize data model by your customized one.</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>In your customized portal tasks HTMLDialog, the customized data model and filter container should be passed as parameters to components (refer to <code>PortalTasks.xhtml</code>).</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="strong">Advanced usage:</emphasis> Portal supports storing/restoring filters. Your filter class (extends <code>TaskFilter</code>) is stored in business data.
                            Properties stored user input values should be persisted, properties controlled logic should not be persisted to reduce persisted data size in business data.
                            Use annotation <code>@JsonIgnore</code> to exclude properties.
                            By default, Portal takes care storing/restoring filters. If you want to customize storing/restoring filter data, do it in your data model class (extends <code>TaskLazyDataModel</code> class).</para>
						<para>By default, filters are stored/restored in process model level. You can change this by setting the ui:param <code>filterGroupId</code> in <code>PortalTasks.xhtml</code> to a new Long value.
							<tip>
								<para>If you have multiple case lists in your project, you may want to set <code>filterGroupId</code> to an unique identifier for each of your <code>PortalTasks.xhtml across your projects</code></para>
							</tip> 
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</sect3>
		</para>
	</sect2>
	<sect2 xml:id="axonivyportal.customization.taskwidget.howtooverridedataquery">
		<title xml:id="axonivyportal.customization.taskwidget.howtooverridedataquery.title">How to override task widget's data query</title>
		<para>
			Override the <code>BuildTaskJsonQuery</code> callable process of PortalKit and build your own query to effect the data of task widget, task categories and statistic widget.
		</para>
		<para>
			Apply the following steps in case you would like to provide data for task list after navigating to task list from your page, e.g. clicking on a bar chart then opening the tasks of that bar:
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>Use the <code>OpenPortalTasks</code> callable process with the <code>TaskView</code> parameter. It is used to define which information are displayed in TaskWidget.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Refer to TaskView, TaskSearchCriteria, TaskQueryCriteria to build your TaskView</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
<screen>
TaskLazyDataModel dataModel = new TaskLazyDataModel();
dataModel.getQueryCriteria().setTaskQuery(YOUR_TASK_QUERY); // Set your TaskQuery
dataModel.getSearchCriteria().setInvolvedUsername(true); // Use this code line if you would like to display the tasks for all users
out.taskView = TaskView.create().dataModel(dataModel).showHeaderToolbar(false).createNewTaskView();
</screen>
		</para>
	</sect2>
	<sect2 xml:id="axonivyportal.customization.taskwidget.customtaskdelegate">
		<title>Custom task delegate</title>
		<para>
			Portal allows to customize the list of users and roles that a task can be delegated to. This can be done following these steps:
		</para>
		<orderedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>Introduce a Axon.ivy project which has <code>PortalTemplate</code> as a required library and its own <code>PortalStart</code> process. Refer to step 1, 2, 3, 4 in <link linkend="axonivyportal.customization.taskwidget.howtooverideui">override task widget's UI</link> guide.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>In your project, override the callable subprocess <code>CalculateTaskDelegate</code></para>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/TaskWidget/CalculateTaskDelegate.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>The callable subprocess data contains the current user <code>in.currentUser</code> and the current task to be delegated <code>in.task</code>. The lists <code>in.users</code> and <code>in.roles</code> contain all possible users and roles that the task can be delegated to. Modify those two to have your own delegate list.</para> 
			</listitem>
		</orderedlist>
	</sect2>
</sect1>
