<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sect1 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="axonivyportal.customization.buildyourownportal">
	<title xml:id="axonivyportal.customization.buildyourownportal.title">Build your own portal</title>
	<sect2 xml:id="axonivyportal.customization.buildyourownportal.buildyourownportalusingportalkit">
		<title>Build your own portal using Portal kit</title>
		<para>
			<orderedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Create a new project that depends on <code>PortalTemplate</code>.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Create new home page
						<orderedlist>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									Create a new <code>HTML Dialog</code> for your home page and then use <code>ui:composition</code> to define template which you use inside. If you want to keep the look of default homepage, then choose <code>DefaultHomePageTemplate</code>.
									
									<tip>
										Find more information about templates at <link linkend="axonivyportal.components.layouttemplates" endterm="axonivyportal.components.layouttemplates.title" />.
									</tip>
                                    <important>
                                      Portal uses some template files in the folder <code>"webContent/layouts"</code> in Portal Template project. Do not create files with the same path and name in your project as they can override the Portal files.
                                    </important>
								</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									Create a new <code>Start process</code> and connect to <code>User Dialog</code> for your home page.
									<mediaobject>
										<imageobject>
											<imagedata fileref="images/BuildYourOwnPortal/new-home-page-connect-process.png" />
										</imageobject>
									</mediaobject>
								</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									Run your application, start your newly created process and see result.
									<mediaobject>
										<imageobject>
											<imagedata fileref="images/BuildYourOwnPortal/custom-portal-home.png" />
										</imageobject>
									</mediaobject>
                                    <tip>
                                    Your new homepage is the default portal homepage. You can customize it. Reference at <link linkend="axonivyportal.customization.portalhome" endterm="axonivyportal.customization.portalhome.title" />.
                                    </tip>
								</para>
							</listitem>
						</orderedlist>						
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Set category for tasks
						<para>
							To categorize tasks, set values for <code>Category</code> field. Task category can be multi-level if it is separated by slash <code>/</code> signs, as below.
							<mediaobject>
								<imageobject>
									<imagedata fileref="images/BuildYourOwnPortal/task-category-config.png" />
								</imageobject>
							</mediaobject>
						</para>
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						How to use feature warning on closing browser/tab
						<para>
							Sometimes when users are working on a task, if they close tab, browser or refresh page then they may lose their current work. It's a good idea to ask users to verify that they truly want to proceed with the action they just invoke. To use this feature, add <code>WarnOnClosingBrowserTab</code> component to the page you want to be affected.
							<para>
								<code>&lt;ic:ch.ivy.addon.portalkit.feature.WarnOnClosingBrowserTab confirmMessage="You may lose your work in progress. Do you want to continue?" /&gt;</code>
							</para>
						</para>
						<para>
							Depending on browser, content of <code>confirmMessage</code> and names of buttons may vary.
							<mediaobject>
								<imageobject>
									<imagedata fileref="images/BuildYourOwnPortal/warn-on-closing-browser-tab.png" />
								</imageobject>
							</mediaobject>
							<tip>
								<para>
									Normally, when using this component, actions that user invoked outside Portal area like closing tab/browser, refreshing page, clicking on a link on bookmark bar of browser will cause browser to display a confirmation dialog. That might cause the feature work incorrectly.
								</para>
								<para>
									Actions that lead to navigation that user invoke inside Portal area like clicking on a link/button, submitting a form will not display any confirmation popup.
								</para>
								<para>
									In some cases, user might use javascript to navigate to another page, for example: set value for <code>window.location.href</code> or call <code>location.reload()</code>.
								</para>
								<para>
									If that happens, add this to your javascript function: <code>showConfirmDialogBeforeUnload = false;</code>
								</para>
							</tip>
						</para>
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</orderedlist>
		</para>
	</sect2>
</sect1>
